The history of the role of infinity in math is
very interesting, and will have its own video soon.
For now just note, that due to various paradoxes, infinity was only
accepted theoretically. Meaning that the sentence for all y, there exists an
x such that x is greater than y. was accepted
But it was not accepted that there exists an x for all y, such that
x is greater than y, since such an x would be a truly infinite set.
It took this man right here, Georg
Cantor to develop a theory of infinity.
The first obstacle we encounter is the seeming paradox we
encounter when trying to compare the sizes of infinite sets.
For example, if we compare the size of the natural
numbers with the set of square numbers...
on the one hand, the set of natural numbers seems
way larger, since most numbers are not perfect squares.
And in fact the difference in size increases with larger numbers.
The squares make up 10 percent of numbers less than 100.
1 per cent of numbers less than 10K
and 0.1 percent of numbers less than a million and so on.
But on the other hand, every natural number has exactly one square. So, at
infinity, we have to admit that the two sets have the same size.
Now, to most of you, this just means that
sets are either finite or infinite, and once they
are infinite, their size cannot be increased or compared.
But to Cantor, the defining characteristic of size, was whether the
two sets could be put into correspondence with each other. So,
to Cantor, these two do literally have the same size
and Cantor's friend Dedekind defined a set to be infinite
if and only if it could be put into 1
to 1 correspondence with a proper subset of itself.
So, the existence of this 1-1 mapping just
shows that the natural numbers are infinite.
Cantor then showed how to put the rational numbers
and even the algebraic numbers (which include certain
irrational numbers like the square root of two)
into 1-1 correspondence with the natural numbers.
Some would say that set theory was born when Cantor showed that
this pattern breaks once we hit the Real numbers. Meaning that there
is no way to put the naturals and reals into 1-1 correspondence.
And therefore the set of real numbers are a larger infinite set
We sketch this proof now.